um it's a great pleasure
to introduce uh thomas parr
today
um very briefly about his background so
he started medical school in
2012 i guess yeah at the ucl
and did did also like a bachelor
there with a focus in new science
in
he started his p i hope it's uh
everything is correct he started his
films
working working together with carl
fristen
and darren reese
um
so i think thomas is really like the
person who most frustrated me i mean i
was at the at the phil yeah so a long
time ago i was fascinated by like the
idea of the free energy principle and uh
carl tristan and really started going uh
learning about boltzmann equations and
uh some kind of like message passing and
so on so forth yeah and over years and
years
and
then in
2016-17
i realized that uh suddenly a number of
papers were coming out which became much
more accessible and on these paper there
were always like one name yeah too
and
so i looked into that and i realized
that there is one person out there
who is uh
so young and who just started his phd
when he was able to go all through this
um extremely complicated
um math and ideas uh so easily yeah that
i thought i should really give up
thinking about the free energy principle
at all and more impressively um i think
a couple of months ago even like a book
came out like um about like active
influence uh
where he is like the first author on um
and i really can recommend this book
it's a it's a fantastic introduction to
active inference to the free energy
principle so it's a really really
great pleasure to have you here tonight
uh thomas and i'm really looking forward
uh to your talk yeah um
thanks for joining yeah
well thank you very much for the very
nice and
the well the invitation and the very
nice introduction as well
um first of all can you hear me okay
yes
okay
and next thing is to see whether i can
successfully share my screen
uh let's try this
so
i'm assuming you can see the powerpoint
and now hopefully in full screen
perfect
great
um
so
so today um i realized that you've
already had a talk from ryan smith
previously so i'm assuming
he's given
an excellent overview of active
inferences as he always does
um and i wanted to take the opportunity
to focus in on something a little bit
more specific um in in this talk which
is thinking about
how
how dealing with active inference lets
us think about neurobiology and how we
can start to make connections and form
neurobiological theories from um from
the principles
and so i'll start just by giving an
introduction that i i
think will hopefully give everybody who
a little bit of a refresher on active
inference and the basic principles
um and
although there are some technical
elements to it i'll try to make it as
intuitive as possible and it really
doesn't matter if you get all the
technical detail through this it's just
to hope to
build some intuitions
and so i i tend to like to start talks
with this slide which just shows two
different sorts of system
the one on the left is one that
just gradually diffuses over time sort
of loses form becomes progressively less
interesting
whereas the one on the right despite
having the same amount of randomness
built into it manages to maintain its
form over time
and a useful starting point in thinking
about active inference is thinking about
what the difference between these two
sorts of systems are and
how how the one on the right is able to
maintain its form and resist this
diffusive um
the effect of these random fluctuations
that are forcing it in all sorts of
different directions
um and it's often useful to reformulate
this in terms of in terms of the
probability density or the change in the
probability distribution of all of these
little particles over time so again you
can see on the left we've got something
that's just diffusing out into nothing
and on the right we get something that
behaves from a proper ballistic level
pretty much statically
um and it's really those on the right
that we're interested in those
biological creatures are able to
maintain their form are able to resist
the effects of what the environment does
to them
now we if we sort of write down the
kinds of dynamics that we need for a
single particle or single part of the
system to try and maintain this form
what we get to is is a system that
i think quite intuitively
um
always moves when it can from regions of
low probability to regions of high
probability
so we interpret this final distribution
it gets to as some steady state
all we need to do to maintain that in a
random environment is to always try and
climb up hill of the probability
gradients and then almost by definition
we end up spending more time in highly
probable states and less time in more
improbable states
and this is sort of the starting point
really for active influence because we
now have this notion that we're
climbing probability gradients and we
have some distribution that we're
effectively trying to maximize
and we can link that back to ideas like
the bayesian brain
the idea that the brain is using some
model of the world around it to generate
predictions um and and then is
drawing inferences about the data that
it actually obtains so sensory
information coming in through our eyes
ears through our skin
that we can then use to draw inferences
about the causes of those data
um so
here we've got the idea that there's
some states of the world x that are
causing some sensory data why
um
we're then forming some posterior
beliefs so beliefs about the causes
given the data
um
and we're doing this using a generative
model that comprises a likelihood and a
prior so prior being how plausible are
the things out there in the world before
we've made any observations the
likelihood being
how likely the observations we've made
are given the states of the world or
given our hypotheses about what caused
them
and together we refer to these two
things as a generative model
now the posterior distribution is what
happens when we invert that model where
we where we find the
probability of some causes given the
data
and the final term we've got at the end
here is referred to either as an
evidence or a marginal likelihood and
that's because in the context of
bayesian statistics we often use a
marginal likelihood as a measure of the
fit of the model to
the data that it's trying to explain
because how much evidence do those data
afford some model of the world
and together we can think of these as
being an inversion of generative model
now the reason i put this here is that
we can see that the dynamics that i'm
showing in the upper left
can be interpreted as the process of
maximizing the evidence of some model
maximizing the fit between the brain's
model of how the world works and how the
world and then engages with the model or
engages with the brain by presenting it
data
and broadly there are two ways of doing
that the first is as we've already
spoken about is changing your beliefs
based upon new data such that you get a
better fit to the world
the other way which i think is one of
the key ideas in active inference
is that you generate actions based upon
your beliefs that change the world to
make it more like your model
and this is sort of the key idea that
underwrites active inference that that
all we're trying to do is maximize the
evidence as a model of our world
um
and we can either do that through
perception by changing our model or
through action by changing the world
but together they come under one um one
single objective sometimes referred to
particularly by people like the acapella
as self-evidencing
now i want to go a little bit into
the structure of generative models and
specifically the ways we can we can
think about and the ways we can notate
generative models
because it often helps to move from a
slightly more mathematical abstract
description to a more graphical notation
that i think often gives a much better
intuitive sense of what's going on
so to do that i'm going to start with
this idea that model evidence is is
effectively what we get out once we've
integrated out all of the causes and
from our model
uh by which i mean
if you take account of all of the things
our model predicts
and then we we take into account the
prior probabilities of all of the all of
the things that are causing um
those data
uh we can then work out what the
probability of the data are under that
model
but the model the model itself takes
account of
the things that are being generated so
our sensory data and also the things
that are causing them simply a joint
probability distribution involving all
of these things so i'm now interpreting
this graphic up on the left as and
depending upon some generative model
where we've effectively integrated out
everything that we
we don't need to determine um explicitly
now generative models will often have
some interesting structure and in fact
if they don't have interesting structure
then they're not interesting generative
models
and normally that structure manifests as
a factorization of this joint
distribution but not everything depends
upon everything else
um and so we can often factorize it and
here i'm just showing a completely
arbitrary factorization of some general
model um where we have certain
dependencies so y depends directly upon
x1 and x2 but not directly upon x3 and
so on
and the reason it's useful to think
about this factorization is because we
can then express a graphical version of
this model
that provides a bit more intuition as to
what's going on
so the way we do that or one way that we
can do that is using something known as
a factor graph
and the idea is that we take each of
these factors in turn middle or square
and then we draw an arrow to whatever
whatever's on the left of the
probability um factor we're interested
in so here an arrow towards the y
because we're saying the probability of
y
conditioned upon or depending upon the
other two things and then we attach
those to the same square
we then move on to the next factor for
another square and
we then attach the relevant variables
together
in exactly the same way
and we carry on doing that until we have
a picture of what our model is like so
now instead of having to look at this
equation you can look at this and say
okay well x3 causes x1 x4 causes x2 and
together x1 and x2 relate to or
together generate our data y
this is just to demonstrate several
models you may be familiar with
generally and the fact that we we're
often implicitly using these kinds of
generative models without necessarily
thinking about it so when we're
performing a principal components
analysis we're often taking some
um
some distribution of some variable x
we're then mapping that to a higher
dimensional space y
um and then
and that's our sort of model of how the
data that we're working with are
generated
so what we can then do when we perform a
principal components analysis is take
our high dimensional data y work out how
you go back from the y to the x and that
gives you all of your specific principal
components and the directions that have
been stretched in various different ways
same principle applies for things like
canonical various analysis where you've
got some set of uh variables then mapped
to two different sorts of data by
stretching them and
and distorting them in various ways and
the challenge is how do you get back to
the the common uh
hidden variable common cause for both of
those data sets
and we do the same sort of thing with
something like clustering analysis where
here the model says we have we're
effectively sampling from one of several
different clusters with different
probabilities uh we're then generating
some point in space depending upon which
cluster it falls in and the process of
um of inference is again undoing this
it's finding the posterior by taking a
point in the cluster and saying well
which cluster is that from so going from
the wide to the s
so that's a sort of brief introduction
to the idea of generative models the um
the role they play in active inference
some key examples and some of the
notations i'm going to use as we go
forward
what i've said so far has been
relatively abstract and in the next
section i want to try and work from
those sort of
general principles and these slightly
abstract notions through to something
more specific and more neurobiological
the first thing we're going to do to get
there is to introduce one more abstract
concept which is that of a mock-off
blanket
a mark of blanket comes up in all sorts
of places in active imprints but i'm
going to use it in a very specific way
here
and and this is to talk about
conditional independence
and what i mean by conditional
independence is that if you have
if you have
two different sets of variables so here
i've notated them as the mu and the eta
the markov blanket b is the set of set
of variables that render the other two
completely independent of one another
that mean that if you know everything
about the blanket knowing something
about mu tells you nothing new about an
eta
to give you an example of this
one of the examples that most people are
familiar with is the idea of a markov
chain
where you have
a sequence of events in time so
something that happens in the past then
influences the present which then
influences the future with no direct
influence from the past to the future
without going via the present
so if i know everything there is to know
about the present knowing something
about the past tells me nothing new
about the future and vice versa so in
that sense the present is the markov
blanket that separates the past from the
future
now this is a very useful concept when
we're dealing with graphical models or
generative models that have some
interesting factorization structure and
i'll try and explain why
the markov blanket is often referred to
as uh or can often be identified by
identifying
variable we're interested in so let's
say we're interested in the variable x2
then you find the parents of x2 so the
things that caused it the children with
x2 so the things it causes and the
parents of its children and that that
gives you the markov blanket of x2
now the significance of this is that
knowing this means that
if we know about the blanket it doesn't
matter what else is going on in the
generative model you know this might be
some tiny section of a huge generative
model with many many variables in
but we don't need to know about those
variables all we need to know about are
the blanket variables so we can
effectively ignore everything else if
what we're interested in is x2
now how does this then matter the
neurobiology
well i think the answer to that is that
the brain is an extremely sparse
structure that synaptic message passing
does not involve connections between
every different neuron in the brain to
every other neural brain there are a
small number of relatively speaking of
um synapses between any neuron and um
and its neighbors or
or neurons elsewhere in the brain
and so we can make an argument that if
the brain is performing inference
without lots of different variables
all it needs is to know the the
structure of the generator model and the
variables that sit in that markov
blanket or at least the neurons that are
representing those other variables
and that tells us that we can then when
we're inverting that mole when we're
performing inference what i'm showing
here is just one example of an inference
scheme
we can
we can express the uh the dynamics of
that neuronal message passing in terms
of
connections from the other neural
populations that are representing
the variables in that markov blanket
the details of
this aren't that important but it this
is one example of a an inference scheme
known as variational message passing
here formulated is a gradient scheme in
terms of some dynamics um which has
relevance for
um for modelling neural populations
where interest and how the dynamics of
those populations evolve over time
um and we can sort of do this
recursively we can couple together lots
of different parts of this system
um
where the things that have been
connected up are are just the mark of
blankets of them of different
populations
here i've expressed it in terms of an
error term that this epsilon um which
effectively represents the gradient of
the free energy objective which is used
as a an approximation to that marginal
likelihood or evidence that i spoke
about earlier
and then some beliefs about or
expectations about um that variable so
we can now use our the errors in our
predictions to update those variables
and once we've written down the dynamics
of this um sort of system we can
simulate things like firing rates we can
simulate the dynamics and the behavior
of
these networks of neurons passing
messages between one another um as a
means of performing a form of inference
and
thus
uh self-evidencing
um
i know this is probably still seeming
relatively abstract but i think what
will hopefully help is if we then go
through some examples thinking about
specific kinds of generative model and
how that might then affect
um the kind of message passing we would
see in a brain
and the first step to thinking about
that which i think is very important
when we think about really useful
generative models is they will all
typically have a temporal aspect to them
but as biological creatures we deal with
things that evolve in time
and so as we're thinking about how do
you formulate a generative model that
has that kind of dynamic aspect to it
and there are several different answers
to that and and one of them is we we use
something known as as a taylor series
approximation um so we start by saying
okay at the current time what what is
the
value of some variable x in the world
and this may be some continuous variable
it may be where my arm is in space
if we then want to know how it's going
to evolve in time we could then say well
let's take the next element of our
taylor series approximation let's take
account of its velocity and that tells
us a little bit more about the
trajectory that my arm might be on
we can then take another valve which is
the current acceleration of that um of
that position and we get a slightly
better approximation to the trajectory
and the more terms we add in
the greater approximation we have of the
trajectory of the greater representation
we have in the trajectory just as a
series of numbers uh where those numbers
are my current position my current
velocity acceleration etcetera
so we could formulate a generative model
by trying to predict each of these
coefficients of this taylor series or
each of these
generalized coordinates of motion as
they're sometimes referred to
an alternative is we just say at time
one where will i be at time two where
will i be and we simply represent it in
terms of the sequence of points over
time
often uh when we're discretizing time in
this way we often we also discretize
space so we might say okay where am i in
some discretized scheme am i in location
one two three four or five at each
different time points
um and so we have two two different ways
of accounting for how things might
evolve over time and each of these can
be useful in slightly different
circumstances
so if i were dealing with a sequential
decision-making task it may be much more
efficient for me to say okay
the first move i'm going to make is this
then the second one is this the third
one is this and dealing with something
very sequential that might also be
important in in sort of language
processing where you have to think which
words you're going to put together in a
sequence and we're dealing with discrete
variables over time because words are a
categorical entity that's supposed to
continue on as opposed to lying on a
continuum
however if i were dealing with movement
or the responses i'm getting from some
photoreceptor in my retina it may be
much more sensible for me to be working
in continuous time thinking about how
things evolve at a continuous scale
so what i'm showing here is an example
of a generative model and the associated
message passing scheme
when formulated in terms of this
continuous time scheme
so what we've got here is a factor graph
at the top this blue element
that uses exactly the same sort of
formulation that we've been discussing
so far so we have some variable here
which might represent our our um
position which then predicts our
velocity at that time which then
predicts the acceleration at that time
so we have a series of predictions here
about
the coupling between different orders of
motion
at each point those are predicting some
sort of data here are y's which
represent the
the
current position of our sensory data the
current velocity the current
acceleration
what i'm showing lower down here is the
message passing scheme we get when we
take account of the markov blankets of
each of these variables so the markov
blanket here for the
the velocity would include the position
and the acceleration but also the data
i've got about those things um and some
prior beliefs about
about other variables in our model
and so we'd end up connecting those
things up
and although it looks like a bit of a
mess of connections it's still fewer
connections than the total number
connections you would get if you map
everything to everything else
what we've got here takes the form of
effectively a predictive coding style
scheme um which people may be familiar
with and the idea that you can you can
hierarchically predict um
predict some
data and you can predict the thing
that's predicting that data those data
and by
observing the errors in your prediction
of the data you update your prediction
which then
cascades up a hierarchy allowing you to
update subsequent
predictions
what i'm showing you here is the
equivalent model formulated in terms of
discrete time and in this case discrete
space as well so here we have a state at
time t minus one which generates a state
at time t which generates a state at
time t plus one
at each of those time points we're
generating some observable outcomes
which are represented as the o's
i have a variable pi here that
represents alternative trajectories i
could i could pursue so alternative
policies or plans alternative ways i
could change the sequence of events
and again we have um underneath the
message passing scheme that could
perform inferences about this sort of
model
um and you can see that the message
passing scheme to some extent looks like
an inversion or
or as loosely a sort of mirror image of
the generative model because all it's
doing is taking each step that was
performed to generate some data and then
inverting those steps one at a time so
it's just going backwards from the data
to arrive at the causes of those data
now
what i've got shown here on the left
is just a
sort of cartoon image
of
some of the key connections in cortical
micro circuits so here we've got
superficial brandal cells as uh as sp
uh spiny stellar cells as ss
deep pyramidal cells is dp and
inhibitory into neurons is the double
eyes
um and this is clearly an over
simplification of
what is a very complex connectivity
structure
but the reason i'm showing this here is
that
if we know something about this
connectivity structure we know about
some of the key patterns we can start to
ask how can the the sorts of models that
we've spoken about over the last couple
of slides then be
um
interpreted in terms of the micro
circuits that could help um the
could help
implement these in a biological system
so what i'm going to show in the middle
is an example of a
continuous states-based predictive
coding style model
that
has all the same elements as in the
slide i showed you before that are now
mapped so that some of the connections
coming in and out of it
um loosely map to those associated with
a known cortical anatomy
and we can do exactly the same thing
here with the discrete state-space model
and think about how we can
assign those roles um associated with
the
roles of different cortical layers
and and then use that as a way of
forming hypotheses
now what i'm showing you on this slide
is not it's not necessarily the last
word on this and you could formulate
several different hypotheses about how
these two things map together and that's
where a lot of interesting science
happens this is just one example of how
we can
associate what we know about cortical
microcircuitry and anatomy with what we
know about the anatomy of message
passing for some simple generic forms of
generative model
what i'm going to try and do over the
rest of this presentation is to take the
connections coming out of this out of
each of these um points and to try and
think about how those might um all the
roles there might those might play when
we take an active inference approach and
the sorts of structures in the brain
that might be involved in uh dealing
with those
dealing with those things
i'm going to start by talking about
movement and reflexes
so here the kinds of things we're
interested in are the connections that
leave
the cortex and go to areas like
the spinal cord and the motor neurons
the predictions that we can we can then
make about the um
what we're seeing here is the in the
central plot and the g that's been
circled in red
is a prediction about the sort of data i
might expect to observe which may here
be proprioceptive data consequent on
particular sorts of action
and we can think of this quite simply if
we think about the structure of a reflex
arc so um what i've got here on the
lower part is just the the same marginal
likelihood or model evidence that we've
dealt with before this idea of
it being a measure of the fit of a model
both in terms of its accuracy the
accuracy with which it predicts some
data
and and
the simplest least complex version of
the model that will work for that
what do we do when we change the data
well we try and make the data more
accurate
in relation to our model by
by trying to align the data with our
predictions
so when we think of the structure of a
reflex arc where we can interpret it as
some descending prediction coming from
the motor cortex saying what is the
proprioceptive data i expect to observe
by comparing that with the
proprioceptive data that's actually
coming into the spinal cord through the
dorsal horn with that prediction we then
get a
potentially a mismatch between the two
that can be used to generate action by
the ventral horn generating
movements and contractions and muscles
that then um try to fulfill these
predictions
i'll show you just an example of of a
simulation of
an arm using active inference that has
these sort of reflex arcs built in and
all we're doing here is we're just
tapping on the biceps tendon and where
the red arrow is pointing and we're just
seeing the reflexive response that we're
getting
as a consequence of effectively inducing
this additional piece of sensory
proprioceptive information by stretching
that tendon
we induce the mismatch between the
prediction that's coming down and the
um and the data that's coming out and
that man that
is corrected then by generating this
additional movement
interestingly we can do things by
manipulating the confidence of those
predictions and sometimes get things
like bigger reflexes and hyper reflex
reflexes the sort you might see in
clinical populations with spinal cord
injuries
and and so you can see the reflex is
slightly larger than it was before and
slightly brisket
uh i'll show you another example of this
same idea where now we've
developed a mapping between the micro
circuit and the
anatomy of the oculomotor brainstem so
here starting from the superior
colliculus the
um
the rough the rostral uh interstitial
nucleus of needle longitudinal vesiculus
and various other centers
and and the cranial nerves that are
responsible for generating eye movements
so cranial nerve three and cranial
nerves and
six here
um are seen here as resulting from uh
these error terms so we're predicting
how i would expect my eyes to move
um and any error in the current position
of the eyes is corrected by generating
eye movements so by inducing different
priors on top of um on top of this model
different predictions about where i'd
expect the eyes to be we can actually
then generate different sorts of eye
movements using a predictive coding
style active inference scheme
where the key thing is that the
predictions can be fulfilled by actually
changing the positions of our muscles
and positions of our eyes
so that sort of provides a very brief
overview and a couple of examples
dealing with the
role of
reflexes and
predictions in generating movements but
it doesn't really tell us anything about
how movements are chosen how movements
are selected and you don't necessarily
get any intelligent behavior out of that
and for that we need to start looking at
different sorts of structures and
different parts of this generated model
and here the key thing i want to focus
on is the role of the basal ganglia and
which here we're going to associate with
the computation of something known as
the expected free energy
and i'll try and describe what that is a
little bit more in some of the
subsequent slides
so
what i'm showing here is a mapping of
some of the um subcortical but some
cortical anatomy or
more accurate i should say that this is
a mapping between parts of our
bayesian message passing scheme parts of
the
model inversion when we're dealing with
ability to plan and make decisions
um
to
some of the known subcortical anatomy of
the brain
and the key thing i want to focus on is
this g that his hair depicted him as
part of the um
as part of the striatum
so the things that are feeding into this
uh are what we're getting from the
cortex here which is some prediction of
the outcomes we'd expect if i were to
pursue a particular course of action
which is this subscript pie
and the
um another sort of error term here which
is how far away is is um
are those predictions from
my preferences about how the world
should be my prior beliefs about
how um the kind of data that i would
actually actively seek
out and act
to get
together those are used to calculate our
expected free energy
which we can then use to formulate
beliefs about policies by saying that um
the policies we would select the plans
we would engage in are those that we
would expect to be associated with the
lowest um expected free energy
and to put that more formally um we're
saying that we're going to give a prior
belief
that um
the policies the series of actions we're
going to choose are going to be those
associated with the maximum information
game tell us the most about um
the world around us
they'll fulfill our preferences
um and then we're going to add an
additional term here which deals with
habitual type
policies and things that we tend to do
because we've learned we behave in a
particular way in those situations now
the combination of this information gain
and preferences are often referred to as
as an expected free energy
and i won't go into the details here but
that's simply because you can rearrange
them mathematically to
make them look very much like the
equation for a free energy or or
marginal likelihood approximation
um
with an expectation around them to say
that these are the
what we would expect given um our
predictions about the data we would
obtain because here we're dealing with
beliefs about the future plums into the
future where we haven't yet had those
data and we need to deal with the
expectations of what those data would be
under different plans that we could
choose
um
so here here we're showing just an
example of the direct pathway through
the basal ganglia um which is normally
thought to facilitate movement and
depends upon this expected free energy
and an indirect pathway which here we've
associated with these kinds of habitual
drives and i'll come back to those a
little bit later on when we deal with
hierarchical models
just to give you a little bit of
intuition as to the information gain
aspect of the expected free energy
because i think most people
uh most people probably understand this
idea of seeking preferences and behaving
to maximize some degree of reward but
many people are less familiar with the
idea of seeking information into the way
that might manifest in these kinds of
models
so as an example um
i'm going to show you just a simple
simulation where we're going to
manipulate some of the different aspects
of the uncertainty in the model
so here um
in the upper left i'm just showing a way
of parameterizing um the the uncertainty
associated with the data generating
process so this is our likelihood
precision our sensory precision
and it effectively says that when this
precision is very high
we can be very certain about the outcome
we'll observe given a particular state
of the world
whereas when it's very low we can
predict everything with very similar uh
probability
we can do something very similar by
manipulating the uncertainty in the
dynamics of the world so again when this
is very high it means that where i am
now is very highly predictive of where
i'll be at the next step in time
whereas when it's very low it means that
pretty much anything at the next time
point is is equally probable
and i'll show you a simple simulation
where these two things are manipulated
just to try and give you an intuition
for what it means to act to maximize
one's information about the world
so the upper simulation here top left
shows um
four panels which can each change at
some point in time to a different color
um with some random
probabilities
um
and the blue line here is designed to
show
effectively an eye tracking trace so
it's a simulated agent who is allowed to
choose which of these panels it wants to
look at at any one time and you can see
it samples them with a relatively even
frequency
in the middle panel what we've done is
we've reduced the precision or increased
the uncertainty associated with the
likelihood in the lower left that
effectively is like turning off the
lights in that location it's effectively
making that lower left location much
more much less informative much more
noisy
and so effectively what we've got here
is a system that then ignores that it
says that i can't get good quality high
quality information from there so i'm
going to look at all of the other
locations rather than rather than this
in the lower left
an analogy for this is if you're
thinking about how you perform a
scientific experiment you would probably
aim to use
if you had a choice between two
different measuring instruments you
would choose the one that gives you more
precise measurements rather than the one
that gives you very noisy measurements
in the lower left
we've manipulated the uncertainty or the
volatility associated with the dynamics
so here what's happened is the upper
left
location is associated with much more
uncertain dynamics
so here what happens is that i end up
sampling that upper left location much
more frequently
and intuitively this makes a lot of
sense because
if you've looked somewhere very recently
normally you will you'll know a lot
about what was there you don't need to
look back there anytime soon however if
it's very volatile if it changes quite
uh
with some degree of randomness and you
have very little certainty about the
state of it after you've looked away
you'll look back with a much greater
frequency so we've effectively decreased
the inhibition of return in this
location by increasing its volatility or
decreasing the precision associated with
its um with the dynamics in that
location
the aim of this was just to show you
this sort of emerging behavior just by
having an information seeking objective
by um by having a prior belief that
we're going to act to minimize some
expected free energy one component of
which is to maximize our information
about the world
now the next thing i want to come on to
is the role of hierarchical generative
models
and one of the key benefits of having a
hierarchical model is that we can now
deal with things that evolve over a
range of different time scales
we might have some things that evolve
very slowly
and some things that evolve very quickly
and to some extent we can separate out
the two and use slowly evolving things
to to
to help us
predict what's happening at the faster
level
and here the key things to denote are
all of these connections between higher
cortical regions and lower cortical
regions which manifests both in the
um
in the
discrete and continuous state space
models and so it's worth them thinking
about what the role of these are and how
that manifests in terms of the
generative models we've been dealing
with before
and it's really this that links back
into
the the idea of predictive coding as
many people know it
and you've probably seen graphics of
this sort in the past where we have a
range of cortical regions that are each
making predictions about the others and
so here going from going from the right
to the left we've got a series of
predictions and as these
dark black lines
with prediction errors passed back up
using these these dashed lines that then
allow us to correct at each level
and all this this graphic shows is a
simplification of the graphic on the
previous slide
so i want to give you an intuition for
why this is useful using a couple of
examples so the first example i'm going
to use is one from the domain of active
vision
um so imagine imagine you're doing a
task now where you have to fixate on
this cross in the center
and i'm and maintain that fixation and
show you a stimulus but maintain
fixation on the cross stimulus is going
to disappear
and then your next task is to perform an
eye movement to the location where the
stimulus appeared
it's a very simple task of the sort was
used frequently in monkey
electrophysiology and
all throughout neuroscience
but it's an interesting one because it
has several different components to it
that i think
help in terms of
thinking about the utility of
hierarchical models
so
one aspect of this is making decisions
about where you're looking at each of
those time points
and making inferences about which of
several alternative locations
you're going to perform an eye movement
too so simple form of planning here
so that calls into
into action the sort of
discrete
states-based model that we were dealing
with before this partially observable
decision process this set of discrete
sequential time points
and that's often
very highly relevant structure of most
simple tasks in cognitive neuroscience
however we also need to actually move
our eyes we need to uh we need to uh
move our eyes from one location to the
next we need to know how to generate
forces we need to know how to make sure
the eyes come to rest in the right
location given those decisions
and that calls them to play this sort of
continuous state-based predictive coding
style model
so how do we then how do we then combine
the two how do we deal with the
situation where we want to predict a
particular location
um
at a discrete level one of several
alternatives but then also map that to a
continuous motor trajectory
and this is where generative models get
a little bit more complicated
so taking this a bit at a time what
we've got at the top here
is our markov decision process model
this is our discrete states-based model
in discrete time
now at each of those time points we're
no longer predicting data specifically
we're now predicting a short trajectory
formulated in terms of our continuous
state-space models
so at time one we're now going to
predict a short element of our
trajectory um and this is very much like
the sort of clustering model i showed
you much earlier that you take a
discrete point and you map it to a point
in continuous space with some
probability
at the next time
we then predict the next bit of that
continuous trajectory
so our priors for our continuous model
are now
inheriting from the predictions from the
discrete state space model and then we
can do the same thing again at the next
time point and and so we can
create a discrete sequence from our um
our sequential model
and at each point in that sequence
associate that with a short trajectory
in continuous space that then predicts
our continuous data
allowing us to then predict the
proprioceptive information we would
expect to get from the eyes when we're
performing a task of this sort
and you can see that that we now develop
a hierarchical structure also in
thinking about the relationship between
the bits of the message passing scheme
so here we've got the discrete bit of
our message passing scheme our
discrete micro circuit and a bit of the
continuous micro circuit here and the
interactions between the two of those
we're making predictions from the
discrete one to the continuous one and
then passing arrows backwards to allow
us to to update
the um discrete element
so
interpreting this again
neurobiologically imagine
that say we have some element of the
cortex perhaps the frontal line fields
that's making predictions about one of
several alternative locations i could i
could direct my gaze
we can then map that via
sort of output of the basal ganglia and
the predictions about what policy i'm
going to pursue
um
through to areas like the superior
colliculus which then might make use of
predictive coding style
networks of the sort depicted here
to then generate eye movements as we've
seen before
and just to show you that in action we
imagine that these are population of
neurons that at each time point trying
to predict one of several um
in this case three different locations
at four different time points
we can then map that through uh
structures like the superior colliculus
and this is supposed to sort of cartoon
the idea of a population code in the
spirit colliculus that then results in
the eye movement to each of those
discrete locations
putting it all together we can then
formulate exactly the tasks that i asked
you to perform earlier
and see the result of an active
inference scheme performing that task
and so here you can see it performs it
very successfully by
by predicting sequences of eye movements
that are conditioned upon the
discrete
part of the model and the idea of
maintaining this belief about
where the stimulus appeared and using
that then to direct my policy selection
and eventually the movement i select
i want to give you one more example of
this sort of hierarchical scheme in the
domain of motor control
and to appeal to the same sort of
simulations we were looking at earlier
in terms of the reflexes exhibited by
that arm
the generative model we're going to use
here and is a slightly complicated one
but here effectively involves
transitions between different locations
that an arm could be in or a hand could
be in
which then predicts different locations
in some continuous space
and different locations that a target
might be in um
and that will then allow us to make
predictions about
um
about given where some target is in some
continuous space uh which decision am i
going to make about the alternative
points i could move my arm to
and so here we have the simulation where
we have the target appearing as the
black ball out of the out of the three
balls which is going to change at
various points in time
and our active influence scheme is now
selecting these locations translating
those into predictions of continuous
trajectories and making the appropriate
movements such that it reaches each of
these
these target locations
and what's shown in terms of the the
graphic here is also an
interpretation of message passing in
terms of the known anatomy of the
motor system or part of it
we can perform various lesions to this
and see whether they behave in the same
way that we might expect patient
populations to so here we've
induced a cerebellar lesion um which
effectively um
involves a misestimation of certain
precision terms certain um confidence or
variance parameters
and you see this sort of overshoot
and this kind of a silitry behavior in
the way the arm behaves
that mimics what we might expect from
cerebellar ataxia
and we can look at the higher levels of
the model and actually have multiple uh
hierarchical levels of the discrete
scheme and here what we've done is we've
induced a
lesion in what might represent a frontal
lobe lesion where now the model is able
to perform all the movements with
perfect fluency but every time there's a
change of context it takes quite a while
to adjust to that new context to deal
with a new situation you'll see that
instead of
moving straight there as it was before
there's a lot more hesitancy and a lot
more difficulty constructing that
long-term narrative
because we've broken that
slower hierarchical level
and here a final lesion that we can
introduce is one that reduces my
confidence and policy selection so here
here this
effectively makes me very uncertain
about what i'm going to do next and here
we get a sort of a kinetic type picture
of the sword we might expect in a
parkinsonian type syndrome
so
um
i realized that was quite a lot and i
hope i'm not too far
over
time but i'll just
try and summarize um briefly the key
ideas that we've discussed
so the the first was thinking about this
idea of climbing probability gradients
the idea that to maintain some form over
time
and to persist
we need to
effectively be climbing these
probability gradients all the time
we interpreted those probability
gradients in terms of in terms of bayes
theorem and
connected that to the bayesian brain
and the sort of message passing that
might be involved in
forming inferences
about elements of some generative model
and the role that might have in
cortical micro circuitry
we also discussed the role of action and
the idea that that um one way to make
our model better fit the world is to act
upon it and one way to do that is to
simply reduce any discrepancy between
the predictions from that model and the
um
and the data that's coming in and the
structure of that is is very similar to
the idea of a reflex arc
as is
as is well known throughout
motion neuroscience
um and the
final thing we we thought about was how
we can then construct hierarchical
models that allow us to produce
simulations and theories of
that that deal with much larger scale
networks in the brain and take a full
sort of systems level view of how
particular movements and particular
behaviors are generated
[Music]
through the inversion of particular
forms of generative model
with that i'd like to thank
many people
who have been involved either directly
or indirectly in this work um i'll
mention the book again which was
mentioned at the beginning and a lot of
this talk was loosely following from the
structure and a couple of the chapters
in the book so um if anybody's
interested
um please do do take a look
i'm more than happy to answer any
questions
thank you for your attention